We talked about project scope and pricing structure and how they are interdependent.
تحدثنا عن نطاق المشاريع وهيكل التسعير وكيف أنهما يعتمدان على بعضهما البعض.
Now let's talk a little bit about how these work in real life.
الآن دعنا نتحدث قليلاً عن كيفية عمل هذه الأشياء في الحياة الواقعية.
What kind of pricing structures are most common?
ما هي هياكل التسعير الأكثر شيوعًا؟
How do the clients react in different scenarios?
كيف يكون رد فعل العميل في السيناريوهات المختلفة؟
Firstly, for any sizable project,
أولاً، بالنسبة لأي مشروع كبير
fixing the scope at the start of the project is quite hard.
فإن تثبيت نطاق المشروع في بدايته هو شيء صعب للغاية.
In the last 16 years of my career,
في آخر 16 عامًا من امتهاني لهذه المهنة
whatever software development projects I have seen,
لم يكن هناك بين كل مشاريع تطوير البرمجيات التي رأيتها
there have been hardly any project
أي مشروع
whose requirements did not change significantly by the end of the project.
لم تكن متطلباته قد تغيرت بشكل كبير بنهاية المشروع.
This is not because of human error,
لا يحدث هذا بسبب الخطأ البشري
but because of theoretical limitations.
ولكن بسبب القيود النظرية.
Sometimes, it is just too hard to imagine the end goal in
أحيانًا يكون من الصعب تخيل الهدف النهائي
a very granular way until you start seeing its bits and pieces coming together.
بشكل دقيق حتى تبدأ في رؤية قطعه الصغيرة وأجزاؤه المختلفة وهي تتجمع معًا.
In software projects, especially,
في مشاريع البرمجيات بشكل خاص
the clients often question their own assumptions,
غالبًا ما يراجع العملاء فرضياتهم
change some modules significantly,
أو يغيرون بعض الوحدات بشكل كبير
or change the entire direction of the project midway.
أو يغيرون اتجاه المشروع بأكمله في منتصف الطريق.
Now, that makes a time and material or the [inaudible] model more compelling for
يجعل هذا نموذج الوقت والمادة أو [inaudible] أكثر قوة
freelancing projects because the clients may not even
بالنسبة للمشاريع الحرة لأنه ربما كان العملاء لا
know what they do not know at the start of the project.
يعرفون أصلًا مقدار ما يجهلونه عند بداية المشروع.
But that does not mean that fixed cost projects are not common, they are common.
ولكن هذا لا يعني أن مشاريع التكلفة الثابتة ليست شائعة، فهي بالفعل شائعة.
In fact, they are used in general as long as there is enough buffer,
في الحقيقة هي تستخدم عامة طالما هناك مساحة كافية
including the proposed cost for any significant changes.
تتضمن التكلفة المقترحة لأي تغييرات كبيرة.
I personally prefer the time and material model with
أنا شخصيًا أفضل نموذج الوقت والمادة مع
new clients because that gives the client and myself time to test each other.
العملاء الجدد لأنه يعطيني ويعطي العميل الوقت لاختبار بعضنا البعض.
The client does not have to make a big commitment of plan,
حيث لا يكون العميل ملزمًا بعمل خطة إلزامية ضخمة
nor am I logged in with the client at this chart.
ولا أكون عالقًا مع العميل في هذا المخطط.
Also, the client may not really have the scope of the project defined in
أيضًا، ربما لا يكون لدى العميل النطاق المحدد المفصل للمشروع،
detail and may not sometimes understand the importance of having a detailed scope.
وربما يكون غير مستوعب لأهمية وجود هذا النطاق المفصل.
Thirdly, if you as a freelancer,
وثالثًا، إذا كنت موظف حر
give a fixed cost to the client,
أعطيت العميل تكلفة ثابتة
which according to you is justified based on the effort estimate,
تكون مبررة بالنسبة لك وفقًا للجهد المقدر
the client may not even agree to it and refuse to give the project to you.
فربما لا يتفق العميل معك ويرفض إعطاءك المشروع.
But usually, when you start working on the project,
ولكن عادة عندما تبدأ بالفعل في العمل على المشروع
the client slowly develops an appreciation for the amount of work
يطور العميل ببطء تقديرًا لمقدار العمل
involved and is more liberal and trusting to spend their money on the project.
المطلوب ويبدأ في إنفاق المال على المشروع بالمزيد من الحرية والثقة.
Starting with time and materials pricing not only helps
لا يساعد البدء بالتسعير حسب الوقت والمادة
the client to not make an upfront commitment and test the waters first,
العميل على ألا يلزم نفسه مسبقًا وعلى أن يختبر الأمور أولًا فقط،
it also helps them to learn what it takes to reach the end goal of
لكنه يساعده أيضًا في معرفة ما يتطلبه الوصول للهدف النهائي
the project so they can better evaluate the pricing of the project.
للمشروع حتى يتسنى له تقدير تسعير المشروع بشكل أفضل.